Guide to the Suzanne Caygill papers, circa 1948-1990.
Caygill, Suzanne papers, circa 1948-1990.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Suzanne Caygill papers, circa 1948-1990.
6367
Suzanne Caygill.
19.8 cubic ft.
Video tapes, audio tapes, worksheets, scrapbooks, posters, samples, photographs, slides, and clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Documentation concerning Caygill's Academy of Color.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Suzanne Caygill (1911-1994) was a milliner, dress designer and night club singer as a young adult. She turned her attention to color as early as 1940 and worked the rest of her life creating individual color palettes for clients and teaching design seminars. In the 1950s Suzanne Caygill starred in a self-improvement television program, "Living With Suzanne" which aired on CBS in Los Angeles. In 1980, she published Color: the Essence of You and established the Academy of Color. Michaelin Reamy (Watts), Cornell Class 1960, Suzanne's apprentice and professional assistant from 1988 until Ms. Caygill's death in 1994, arranged and coordinated the donation of the Suzanne Caygill Archives to Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Documentation concerning the Academy of Color including material for students, information about certification and accreditation, worksheets, and scrapbooks, posters, samples, photographs, slides, and clippings used in teaching. Also a set of 24 training video tapes from the Academy of Color including 19 tapes entitled "The Four Seasons"; 3 tapes entitled "Fabrics"; "The Key to Color Harmony," used to introduce clients to her theory; and "Living with Suzanne," excerpts from the television show, ca. 1952. Audio tapes of "The Key to Color Harmony," an abbreviated version of her theory; and "Poetry for Inspiration," in which Suzanne recites some of her favorite poems.
Typed mss. of Suzanne's book, Salon of Color business plan, interior design proposal and related letters, wardrobe design for Lisa Curry, schedule of events for May 1984, Academy of Color certificates, client comments, photograph, miscellaneous letters and schedules, and teaching manuals. Also, "Red Leather Seasons Portfolio" used by Suzanne in her teaching to show examples of the connection between a woman and her costume that fit a season, and various items of clothing, hats, and shoes worn by Suzanne.
Workbook created by Suzanne for Mary Cowies Moore of San Francisco, 1948.
Also, additional newspaper clippings about Suzanne and her work, original layout materials for her Salon of Color and course work, copies of her newsletter "Suzanne Says," and a 33 rpm phonograph record of her poetry readings. Also additional clothing, including a suit, blouse, evening dresses, hat, and a number of fabric evening stoles, some of which were designed by her.
Notebook compiled by Lisa Curry of handouts and class notes from Suzanne's seminars.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Suzanne.; Academy of Color.
Subjects:
Color in clothing.; Color in interior decoration.; Seasons.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 13-15: restricted to permission of the Archivist
Access Restrictions:
Due to the fragility and potential degradation of moving image and sound recordings, viewing and listening is limited to items that have been digitized. If an item is in another media format, you may request to have the item digitized for access. Information on ordering access copies may be found on our Reproductions and Permissions page.
Series List
Series I. Files
Boxes 1, 2, 5, 6, 17, 22, 23, 24, 30
Series II. Videos [Please only use media that has been digitized]
Boxes 3
Series III. Sound recordings [Please only use media that has been digitized]
Boxes 3, 4, 24
Series IV. Slides
Box 4
Series V. Images
Boxes 7-11, 16, 24, Mapcase Folder 1
Series VI. Fabric/clothing
Boxes 12, 18-21, 25-28, Mapcase Folder 2
Series VII. RESTRICTED
Boxes 13-15
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Files
  - Academy Legal Agreements, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Release Agreements, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement: Non-Competitive, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Graduates, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agreements: Accreditation, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agreement: Enrollment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agreements: Methods, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial Agreements, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Approval/Disclosure Statement, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Apprenticeship, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Post Graduate Course, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Enrollment, Student Record, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Applications of Intent and Historical Background, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Privileges/Obligations Policy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oath of a Color Analyst, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Certificate - Color Technician, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Certificate - Color Analyst, 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Graduation Requirements, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Business Methodology, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Student Material, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Student Material - Test: Final Exam in Color, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Test - Color Aptitude, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Student Material - Matching Test, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Evaluation - Administrators, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Student Evaluation and Progress Report, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Attendance Record, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Management Counseling and Termination, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Joyce Clydesdale Lecture, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Student Materials - Supply List, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Metropolitan Museum Paintings and Season, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Animated Flowers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fabrics - Surface Patterns, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Porcelains, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Color Property Charts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Student Material: Pigment Charts, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Student Material: Texture Definitions, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Student Material: Color Mechanics; Color Wheel Assembly, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Academy of Color - spring, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Society of Color Analysts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Department of Education - Academy of Color, 1978-82 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Accreditation: State Department of Education, 1981-83 (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - Academy - Profit/Loss Estimate, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Department of Education, 1981-83 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Department of Education, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Academy: Applications Received, 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Academy Proposal, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Color Mechanics, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Student Material: Color Charts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Worksheets - Season Types, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Harmonies for the Season, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Pigments for the Seasons, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Academy Prospects and Leads, 1981-86 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Academy Schedules - September, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Academy Schedules, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Academy Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Student Material: Color Wheel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Student Material: Color Mechanics, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Student Material: Color Harmony, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Student Material: Color Wheel (brands used), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Suzanne, Color The Essence of You, Millbrae, California: Celestial Arts, 1980, 1980 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Instructions to Hotels, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Assistant Commission Sheet, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Letter & Palette Instructions, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Palette Record, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Palette Instructions - Women, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Palette Instructions - Men, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Master: Purse Palettes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Gift Certificates, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Palette Miniature, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Body Measurements, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Style - Sketches, June 1964 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Palette Forms, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Style - Promotion, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Style for Women, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Style for Men, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Designer Information (label says Manuscripts - Songs), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Costume Forms, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Focal Point Definition Cards, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - Focal Point Analysis, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Masters: Focal Point Analysis, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Psychological Styling, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Fabric Dictionary, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Fabrics - Surface Patterns, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Qualities to Emphasize, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Costumes/Lines, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Versatility in Dress, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Furniture Styles/Costumes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Period Adaptations, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Chart for Personality, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Psychological Style (small binder), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - How to Use Your Room Deciders (board), 1965 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Jack Boggess, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Interiors - Materials for Summer, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Palette Survey, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Interiors: Color Scheme & Sound, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Focal Point for Vibration, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Palettes - Hotel Setup, etc., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Client Forms, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Registration Forms, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Registration Procedures, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Calendars, 1979-1988 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Interior Designing - Upholstery Co., 1979, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - [Four Seasons Beauty Box], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Cosmetics Price Lists/Order Form, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Source - Reupholstering, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Source - Room Dividers, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Source - Storage, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Source - Kitchen Sinks & Fixtures, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Source - Photo Murals, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Source - Metal Finishes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Source - Tile Colors, 1971, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Source - Office Machinery, 1975, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Source - Murals, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Source - Mirror - Wall Fixtures/Hangings, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Source - Tints, 1967, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Source - Furniture - Res/Cont, 1966-1976 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Source - Furniture - Contract, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Source - Bedspreads, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Source - Cement & Stucco Color, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Source - Art, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - [Vanity], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - [Price List], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - [Color Book Dummy], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - [Shades of Brown], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - [Brown, Pink, Black], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Miscellany: Talent Night, Vanity, 1983, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Salon of Color Packet, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Neurosis, Mailing List, Program in Living Color, 1989, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Academy of Color, 1979-1990 (Box 5, Folder 70-72)
  - Academy of Color - Seminar 2, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Evening of Theatre, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 74-75)
  - Wardrobe Mechanics for Men, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Film Catalogue, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Poetry, 1929-1979 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - RSVP Quotes, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photos, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Fabrics, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Paper & Fabric Samples, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Academy Fabric Study, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Certificates, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Suzanne Caygill's business plan, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Color salon - sketches, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Book proposal - "The Four Seasons", n.d. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript - "Color as the Key to Self", n.d. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Personality Package, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Psychological Styling, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Style - lecture, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - misc/unsorted material (Box 17)
  - Workbook created by Suzanne for Mary Cowies Moore of San Francisco, 1948 (Box 22)
  - 4 loose-leaf color notebooks, ca. 1960-1980 (Box 23)
  - Notes and proofs (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Articles (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Misc. items (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbooks (Box 24)
  - Notebook compiled by Lisa Curry of handouts and class notes from Suzanne's seminars and correspondence from Suzanne to Lisa and Robert Curry, 1974-1992 (Box 30)
- Series II. Videos [Please only use media that has been digitized]
  - Academy of Color: Fabric Lesson Part I, n.d.; V-8950-8951 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1752 in Box 29
  - Academy of Color: Fabric Lesson Part II, n.d.; V-8952 (Box 3)
  - Developing the Palette: Anticipating the Type (follows Autumn Part I), n.d.; V-8953 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1753 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Feminine Types Spring - Parts I-III, n.d.; V-8954-8956 (Box 3)
  - The Four Seasons: Feminine Types Summer - Parts I-II, n.d.; V-8597-8958 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1754 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Feminine Types Autumn - Parts I-II, n.d.; V-8959-8960 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1755 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Feminine Types Winter - Parts I-II and Message of the Seasons, n.d.; V-8961-8962 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1756 and DVD-1757 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Masculine Types Spring, n.d.; V-8963 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1757 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Masculine Types Summer and Autumn, n.d.; V-8964 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1758 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Masculine Types Autumn (excerpt), n.d.; V-8965 (Box 3)
  - The Four Seasons: Masculine Types Winter, n.d.; V-8966 (Box 3)
  - The Four Seasons: Message of the Seasons: Spring Summer Autumn Winter, n.d.; V-8967 (Box 3)
  - The Four Seasons: Message of the Seasons: Summer (excerpt), n.d.; V-8968 (Box 3)
    Please use DVD-1759 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons: Message of the Seasons: Autumn (excerpt), n.d.; V-8969 (Box 3)
  - The Four Seasons: Message of the Seasons: Winter (excerpt), n.d.; V-8970 (Box 3)
  - The Four Seasons: Skintone Lesson (Follows Summer Part II), n.d.; V-8971 (Box 3)
  - Living with Suzanne (2 copies), ca. 1950s; V-8972-8973 (Box 3)
  - The Key to Color Harmony (2 copies), n.d.; V-8974-8975 (Box 3)
  - Roy Cook Marketing, August 10, 1981 - DVD (4 copies), 1981; DVD-722-729 (Box 4)
- Series III. Sound recordings [Please only use media that has been digitized]
  - Poetry for Inspiration (5 copies), n.d.; TR-10677-10681 (Box 3)
    Please use CD-2871 in Box 29
  - Suzanne presents the Key to Color Harmony (4 copies), n.d.; TR-10682-10685 (Box 3)
  - Suzanne sings, n.d.; TR-11669 (Box 3)
    Please use digital file
  - A: Color Theory - New York B: Color Theory - the Lights - N.Y., n.d.; 1, TR-10686 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2872 in Box 29
  - A: Magazine - David Ryrr & Suyaree Sap, n.d.; 1, TR-10687 (Box 4)
  - Psychological Style, Los Angeles, Calif., 12/1/86, tape 2, 1986; 1, TR-10688 (Box 4)
  - Re clearance on poetry, etc., Mark Brown, n.d.; 1, TR-10689 (Box 4)
  - Color Your Life, n.d.; 1, TR-10690 (Box 4)
  - Color Theory, New York, n.d.; 1, TR-10691 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2873 in Box 29
  - Psychological Style, Los Angeles, Calif., 12/1/86, tape 3, n.d.; 1, TR-10692 (Box 4)
  - A: Suzanne/ElliotB: Poetry in preparation, n.d.; 1, TR-10693 (Box 4)
  - Color theory (11 tapes), 1984; 2, TR-10694-10704 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2874 and CD-2875 in Box 29
  - Counselor course (9 tapes), 1985; 3, TR-10705-10713 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2876 and CD-2877 in Box 29
  - Psychological Style (8 tapes), 1985; 4, TR-10714-10721 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2878 and CD-2879 in Box 29
  - RSVP (Relaxation, Speech, Voice, Posture) (9 tapes), 1985; 5, TR-10722-10730 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2880 and CD-2881 in Box 29
  - Spring (9 tapes), 1979-1982; 6, TR-10731-10739 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2882 and CD-2883 in Box 29
  - Summer (6 tapes), 1978-1974; 7, TR-10740-10745 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2884 and CD-2885 in Box 29
  - Autumn, 1978-1986; 8, TR-10746-10753 (Box 4)
    Please use CD-2886 and CD-2887 in Box 29
  - The Four Seasons (digital copy of audiocasettes), 1978-1986; CD-1383-1384 (Box 4)
  - 2 copies of a 33 rpm phonograph record, "Poetry for Candlelight", by Suzanne Caygill, n.d.; SR-6320-6321 (Box 24)
- Series IV. Slides
  - Masculine types, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Feminine types, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
- Series V. Images
  - Scrapbook pages, photographs, poem "Colors", n.d. (Box 7)
  - Images mounted on boards, n.d. (Box 8-10)
  - 2 Framed Images of Suzanne, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Red Leather Seasons Portfolio (Box 16)
  - Photos, including Dolores Del Rio, Suzanne Caygill and "Master Class" group photo of women wearing hats designed by Caygill, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Over-size Images on Boards/collages (teaching materials), n.d. (Folder 1)
- Series VI. Fabric/clothing
  - Fabric Samples, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Clothing - including "Nothing Dresses" (silver and blue), n.d. (Box 18)
  - Other clothing, shoes, jewelry and cosmetic cases, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Hats, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Tangerine angora wool dress, jacket, and shawl, designed by Suzanne, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Additional clothing (Box 25-28)
  - Over-size Fabric Samples on Boards (teaching materials), n.d. (Folder 2)
- Series VII. Restricted
  - Contact cards for clients seeking individual palettes, n.d. (Box 13-15)
    These cards contain addresses and phone numbers of clients and occasionally mention the type of palette, eg. vital spring, but do not contain the actual color palette. They also contain billing information for consultation services.